<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="X" level="1">Rehire Retirees</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>10.01</section_number>
<catch_line>Rehire Retirees</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section>This Article governs the terms and conditions of employment of individuals who have retired under STRS rules whom the Board may regularly employ in a position that falls within the bargaining unit.</section>

<section prefix="a">For initial placement purposes on the salary schedule, the employee will receive horizontal credit in accordance with the normal rules, with the further understanding that the employee will be placed at Step 0 of the appropriate column.</section>

<section prefix="b">The employee will receive a one-year limited contract of employment (if employed after the start of the year, such contract will be for the remainder of that school year). Each one (1) year contract shall automatically expire upon the completion of the year and it is not necessary for the Board to conduct evaluations in accordance with Ohio Revised Code 3319.111 or Article VIII or for the Board to take formal action to not reemploy the employee pursuant to Ohio Revised Code 3319.11 or Article XI in order to terminate the employment relationship. If subsequently reemployed, the employee will be awarded another one-year limited contract. In no event will the employee qualify for a continuing contract or multi-year contract. if reemployed, the employee shall advance one (1) year on the salary schedule.</section>

<section prefix="c">Upon employment, the employees will be credited with zero (0) years of seniority and will not retain or accrue seniority.</section>

<section prefix="d">The employee shall not be eligible for severance pay upon separation from employment.</section>

<section prefix="e">A full-time employee shall be eligible to participate in the District’s insurance programs offered to bargaining unit members as identified in Article 18.02 but the Board will pay 80% and the employee will pay 20% of each such benefit. For part-time employees, the Board’s share will be prorated based on the employee’s part-time status.</section>

<section prefix="f">Prior employment in the District is no guarantee of post-retirement employment or a particular assignment. Employees must apply for each vacancy for which they wish to be considered, and compete with other applicants as a part of the selection process.</section>

<section prefix="g">Employees shall be SEA members or Fair Share Fee Payers as provided in the Negotiated Agreement.</section>

<section prefix="h">Employees who are rehired will begin employment with zero (0) days of accumulated sick leave, and will accrue and accumulate sick leave in accordance with the provisions of the Negotiated Agreement.</section>

<section prefix="i">Employees shall not be entitled to tuition reimbursement/professional development stipend identified in Article 18.06 or the sick leave bank identified in Article 14.04.</section>

<section prefix="j">Employees shall be entitled to all other benefits provided by the Negotiated Agreement unless otherwise limited by specific provisions of this Article.</section>

<section prefix="k">The provisions of this Article supersede and prevail over any inconsistent terms that may appear elsewhere in this Negotiated Agreement or in any part 'of the Ohio Revised Code, including but not limited to 3317.13, 3319.08, 3319.11, and 3319.111.</section>

<section>This article does not apply to retired employees who were rehired by the Board before June 1, 2005.</section>
</text>

</law>