<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XV" level="1">Working Conditions</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>15.01</section_number>
<catch_line>School Day</catch_line>
	
<text>(a) A normal working day for all employees including traveling employees shall be 7 1/4 hours in length including a duty free lunch period of at least thirty (30) minutes and a conference! preparation period. Starting times and ending times shall be established by the Principal in each building, but all employees will work a normal working day. Nothing herein should be construed to require that the starting and ending time for each employee in a particular building be uniform. Should the district decide to change starting and ending time for employees, the superintendent will notify the Association president of the district's intent. Employees will be given the opportunity to volunteer for an assignment by August 1.

(b) A building principal, district administrator, or supervisor may schedule a one hour staff meeting per month. If the meeting lasts more than one hour or additional meetings are required during the month, employees shall be compensated pursuant to Article 17.05, Compensation shall be based in quarter hour increments.

(c) Employees will attend one (1) open house per school year not to exceed two (2) hours.

15.02 School Year

(a) The school year shall consist of 185 contract days. One hundred eighty (180) days shall be for instruction and may include two (2) days tor parent-teacher conferences. The remaining five (5) days shall be scheduled with the equivalent of three (3) days being used for teacher directed activities (i.e., in-classroom work day) and the equivalent of two (2) days being used for administration directed activities. The teacher-directed activities will be designated as follows: the equivalent of one (1) full work day for in-classroom preparation/set up scheduled before the first day of school for students, the equivalent of one (1) full day in January, with one-half (1/2) of the day for in-classroom work and one-half (1/2) of the day for employees to complete various activities in or out of the classroom, and the equivalent of one (1) full day for classroom close up scheduled after the last day of school for students.

15.03 Planning/Duty Time - K-5

(a) The normal schedule for each full-time classroom employee shall include at least 200 minutes per week for instructional planning and evaluation conferences, with at least one (1) planning increment during the student day of not less than 35 continuous minutes. The normal schedule for each classroom employee working at least half-time shall include planning time proportional to the number of hours scheduled to work (e.g., half-time = 100 minutes). ln situations where it is impossible to schedule planning time in accordance with this provision, such deviation will be permitted by mutual agreement of the Building Principal and the employee with, if appropriate, additional compensation arrangements.

(b) Scheduled non-classroom duties shall be equitably assigned among all employees of of the building.

15.04 Planning/Duty/Scheduling Assemblies Time - 6-12

(a) Every salaried employee who works half-time or more shall be guaranteed one uninterrupted class period per day for preparation. Every hourly paid employee who works four (4) or more hours per day shall receive one (1) uninterrupted class period per day for preparation. ln situations where it is impossible to schedule planning time in accordance with this provision, such deviation will be permitted by mutual agreement of the Building Principal and the employee with, if appropriate, additional compensation arrangements.

(b) At the start of each school year, the Building Principal will work out with the Department Chairs and/or Team Leaders the methodology for scheduling assemblies during the school year.

(c) The assignment of homerooms and other non-classroom duty, such as cafeteria duty, shall be done in an equitable manner within each building.

15.05 High School Preps

(a) Employees teaching in the High School who are assigned four (4) different and distinct class preparations shall receive $750.00 per year additional compensation for such additional duty. Employees teaching in the High School who are assigned five (5) different and distinct class preparations shall receive $1,000.00 per year additional compensation for such additional duty.

(b) A different and distinct class preparation is defined as any course offering which has an approved textbook(s) and/or course of study and requires a separate, definite lesson plan.

15.06 Class Size

(a) The BOARD will attempt to meet the following student to teacher ratios for classes except for special areas, such as art, physical education, music and health:

(1) Kindergarten - First Grade 22:11

(2) Second - Fifth Grade 23:1

(3) Sixth - Twelfth Grade 24:1

15.07 School Procedures For Employees

(a) Each Principal will provide his/her staff and the ASSOCIATION President with that school's written procedures for staff and students (staff handbook/student handbook) at the beginning of the school year. Any change to these procedures distributed after September will, except in the emergency situations, be reviewed with the school ATLC prior to implementation.

15.08 Substitutes

(a) Every effort shall be made to secure a substitute in the absence of an employee.

(b) If it becomes necessary to have an employee substitute for an absent employee, the following selection procedure to determine which employee shall be required to do so shall be followed:

(1) Prior to the start of each school year, the employees in each building shall be sun/eyed to determine which employees assigned to the building desire to volunteer for substitute teaching duty during the school year. Employees who indicate a desire to volunteer for such substitute teaching duty who are available to do so during the period required will be assigned the substitute teaching duty on a rotating basis.

(2) If no volunteer is available for the substitute teaching duty, the Principal shall have the right to require an available employee to perform the substitute teaching duty. If more than one employee is available during the period, assignments will be made on a rotating basis.

(c) If an employee (other than an employee supervising a study period) is required by the Administration to substitute for an absent employee by taking the full or partial (at least one-half (1/2) of the class) class of such absent employee, the employee will be paid Twenty Dollars ($20.00) per period for such work as an add-to pay.

(d) An employee who is entitled to additional compensation pursuant to the provisions of this Section shall receive a verification of the substitute duty performed from the Building Principal by receiving a copy of the payment request form submitted to the Treasurers Office.

15.09 Facilities for Employees

(a) ln each building, employees shall have at least one room of appropriate size reserved for faculty use.

(b) A telephone shall be made available in each building for personal and professional use.

15.10 Medication

(a) When the employee is required to administer medication to a student, the BOARD shall require the parent(s) to furnish a waiver of liability for said employee and specific instructions regarding such administration. Except for nurses, employees will not be required to administer any medical procedures such as catheterization or injection, except as identified in (b) below, or to render regular hygienic care.

(b) EPIPEN Requirements

All employees shall be trained in the use of the EPIPEN. Training will be during the workday or in-service day and at the Board‘s expense. After receiving training, employees will administer necessary first aid.

15.11 Delayed Start Days

(a) Once each month that school is in session, one day shall be a delayed start day. All classes will be started one hour late on these dates. Dates for delayed start shall be set when the Calendar Committee meets and develops the calendar for each year. The agenda for the delayed start days will be determined for a semester at a time by committee at each building. At the elementary level, a committee shall be made up of one administrator and two employees selected by the Association. At the secondary level, a committee shall be made up of two administrators and four employees selected by the Association. Acceptable activities for delayed start days include, but are not limited to, team, department, vertical articulation and cross curriculum meetings and sharing of processional training.

15.12 Professional Rights

(a) No grade given to a student by an employee shall be changed by any Administrator without prior consultation with the employee.

15.13 Special Education Teachers

(a) Employees teaching in the area of Special Education shall be provided with two (2) days (or the equivalent) of release time, as arranged through their Building Principal, for the performance of related duties specifically associated with their work as a special education teacher such as preparation of l.E.P.'s evaluation, testing, and assessment responsibilities. Additional release time may be approved by the Building Principal as needed.

15.14 Curriculum Development

(a) Employees participating in curriculum development activities shall be paid an hourly rate or stipend for such work as set forth in Section 17.04 or be granted release time at the option of the Superintendent.

15.15 Multiple School Assignment

(a) Employees assigned to more than one (1) school shall be provided with the appropriate time to close, travel and set up. If appropriate time cannot be provided and the employee does not receive the planning time and lunch as required under this Article, then compensatory time or compensation shall be provided.

(b) The administration shall be responsible for the coordination of traveling employees‘ schedules and for securing substitutes for absent traveling employees. lf there are any changes in a Building schedule, it shall be the Building Administrators responsibility who initiates the schedule change to notify the other Building Administrator of the change.

(c) Planning time per day for traveling employees with multiple building assignments shall be at least equal to the length of planning time for other employees at the building at which the traveling employee spends the greater(est) number of hours per day.

15.16 Drug/Alcohol Free Schools

(a) Purpose

The BOARD and the ASSOCIATION agree that quality education is not possible in an environment affected by illegal drug use and/or abuse of alcoholic beverages. The BOARD and ASSOCIATION have established and agree to maintain a drug/alcohol-free educational setting in full compliance with federal, state, and local laws, including the Drug-Free Workplace Act and the Drug-Free Schools and Communities Act.

(b) Employee Assistance Program

Chemically dependent employees are urged to seek help before their dependence causes problems with their jobs.

Recognizing that chemical dependency is a treatable illness which should be dealt with by treatment and education, it is they BOARD‘s policy to prevent chemical dependency and/or offer rehabilitation, rather than to merely discipline employees for substance abuse related problems. To that end, the BOARD and the ASSOCIATION have formed an Employee Assistance Committee consisting of at least one representative from Administration, the SEA bargaining unit, the SCEA bargaining unit, and that group of employees not
represented by either SEA or SCEA, to monitor the Employee Assistance Program which is available to all BOARD employees and their dependents.

The Administration will work with an employee desiring chemical dependency rehabilitation assistance on a voluntary basis. Applicable group health plan coverages, sick leave benefits and leaves of absence policies are available to assist employees who seek rehabilitation. Voluntary rehabilitation and/or inquiries concerning rehabilitation will not be used as evidence of a violation of any BOARD policy.

Where rehabilitation is offered by the Administration in lieu of discipline, such rehabilitation, if elected, is considered involuntary. Involuntary rehabilitation shall be available only one (1)time during an employees tenure of employment with the BOARD, and shall not be available to any employee in lieu of termination for operating any motor vehicle on BOARD business under the influence of alcoholic beverages, or while currently using illegal drugs.

(c) Drug-Free Awareness Program

The Employee Assistance Program referenced in this section will include educational opportunities for employees to obtain information on the dangers of substance abuse and resources available for chemical dependency and rehabilitation. in the meantime, information on drug and alcohol counseling, rehabilitation resources, and re-entry programs, and benefits available to employees in dealing with substance abuse problems will be maintained in the District.

(d) Drug Testing

Nothing in this section shall be interpreted as requiring an employee to submit to urinalysis tests for controlled substances; however, it is understood that the Administration may require such tests to the extent testing is required by federal or state law. In the event such testing is required, the parties will meet and confer regarding the facility or facilities to be used to perform such tests.

(e) Confidentiality

Information provided to administrative personnel concerning medical problems related to substance abuse or chemical dependency of an employee shall be considered part of the employees medical record and shall be treated as confidential. However, performance problems, attendance or rules violations will be documented, reported or otherwise treated as ordinary personnel information even if related to substance abuse or chemical dependency.

(f) Notification

At the beginning of each school year, all employees will receive a copy of the Drug/Alcohol Policy which includes the disciplinary sanctions and a description of the Employee Assistance Program. The annual review of this section of BOARD Policy will emphasize that compliance is mandatory.

(g) Board Policies

The BOARD may adopt policies, rules and procedures to implement the terms of this Section.

(h) Prohibited Conduct

The unlawful manufacture, distribution, dispensation, possession or use, or being under the influence of alcoholic beverages and/or controlled substances (illegal drugs) by any employee, during working hours, on BOARD premises, or at any activity or function sponsored by or related to employment with the BOARD, is prohibited. "Premises" includes vehicles owned by, or being driven on behalf of the Springboro Community City School District, as well as parking lots, playgrounds, and other property owned by Springboro Community City Schools. "Controlled substance" refers to drugs subject to federal or state regulation, making their manufacture, dispensation, distribution, possession or use a crime, this includes but is not limited to Cannabis, Cocaine, Amphetamines, Barbiturates, and Heroine. Medications used as prescribed by a treating physician or dentist are excluded.

(i) Drug-Related Criminal Conviction

Employees convicted (including a guilty or no contest plea) of violating any federal, state or local criminal drug law, where the violation occurred during work hours, or on BOARD premises, must report the conviction to the Superintendent within five (5) business days of a conviction, Where said criminal offense is a minor misdemeanor, the employee shall be referred for involuntary rehabilitation in lieu of a 5-day suspension without pay. Failure to participate in rehabilitation or a subsequent conviction for minor misdemeanor drug-related offenses will result in a 5-day suspension without pay. Convictions for offenses other than minor misdemeanors will result in discipline, up to and including termination, in accordance with contractual and statutory provisions. Failure to report the conviction(s) will result in termination.

(j) Penalties

Violations of the BOARD's Drug/Alcohol-Free Schools Policy will result in discipline up to and including termination, which disciplinary action will be taken in accordance with contractual and/or statutory provisions.

15.17 Smoke Free Environment

(a) No smoking will be permitted in any school building, on any school grounds, in any school vehicles and/or while supervising students.

15.18 Employee Job Descriptions

(a) The Superintendent has developed job descriptions for all current jobs which have been provided to the ASSOCIATION. lt is the prerogative of the Superintendent to develop new job descriptions for bargaining unit positions. Upon development, the Superintendent shall forward copies of proposed job descriptions for new positions and/or for positions which are being revised to the ASSOCIATION President for input prior to formal creation or revision of said positions.

15.19 IEP/504 Meetings

(a) A building principal may direct employees to attend any lEP meeting or 504 meeting that occurs outside the normal teacher working day. Employees who attend five (5) IEP/504 meetings outside the normal teacher working day in one school year will receive a payment of $100 in the last pay in June. Any employee who attends more than five (5) IEP/504 meetings outside the normal working day will receive a payment of $20 per meeting for each such meeting over five (5) meetings in the last pay in June.</text>

</law>