<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="IX" level="1">Vacancies, Assignments and Transfers</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>9.02</section_number>
<catch_line>Voluntary Transfer</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">Employees under contract and recommended for renewal in April will be considered for a reassignment or voluntary transfer, provided the employee does one of the following:</section>

<section prefix="1">prior to the end of the school year the employee provides written notice to the Superintendent of his/her interest in an open vacancy. Said notice shall specify in order of preference, where applicable, the building or buildings desired, grade level desired, and/or subject area desired; or</section>

<section prefix="2">within seven (7) calendar days of the posting of a vacancy, the employee provides written notice to the Superintendent of his/her interest in the position.</section>

<section prefix="b">All employees who apply and who are qualified for new or vacant positions will be considered for such positions. Employees who apply for new or vacant positions, but are not selected for said positions may request a conference with the Superintendent to discuss why the reassignment or voluntary transfer was not granted. The employee may have an ASSOCIATION representative of his/her choice at such a conference. Additionally, the employee may request written reasons why the reassignment or voluntary transfer was not granted.</section>

<section prefix="c">For purposes of 9.01 (d), 9.02(a) and 9.02(b), "considered” means that an employee will be interviewed by a building principal/administrator the first time the employee applies for any position in that building principal/administrator's building. The building principal/administrator does not have to interview the employee again if the employee applies for that position again or for any other position in the building principal administrators building.</section>
</text>

</law>