<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XVII" level="1">Salary Schedule Provisions</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>17.03</section_number>
<catch_line>Supplemental Salary Schedule</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">The supplemental salary schedule base shall be computed as follows:</section>

<section prefix="1">0-3 years experience 13.5% of BA 0
<section prefix="2">4-6 years experience 15.5% of BA 0
<section prefix="3">7+ years experience 17.5% of BA 0

<section prefix="b">Placement on the supplemental salary schedule shal be according to the following guidelines:</section>

<section prefix="1">Years of experience as a paid employee shall be granted for the total number of years experience in the specific activity/coaching field; i.e., football, basketball, track, etc.</section>

<section prefix="2">Assistant coaches appointed to a head coaching position within the same port shall be placed at the lowest experience level which provides a salary higher than their current assistant coach salary levels.</section>

<section prefix="3">Experience in boys and girls sports shall be treated equally with regard to experience, providing such experience is within the same specific activity/coaching field.</section>

<section prefix="c">Adjustments in Index factors for any supplemental position and/or creation of new supplemental positions during the term of this Agreement shall be made if there is mutual agreement between the BOARD and the ASSOCIATION.</section>

<section prefix="d">Notwithstanding the wage rate specified in Appendix X for the Camp Kern Counselor, past experience in the positions where experience has not been applicable shall not be granted. The 1994-95 school year shall be considered the first year of experience for placement on the salary schedule.</section>

<section prefix="e">Development of "Notices of Vacancy" for supplemental positions shall be according to the following guidelines:</section>

<section prefix="1">"Notice of Vacancy" postings shall be prepared for all new supplemental positions prior to posting and filing said positions.

<section prefix="2">It is the prerogative of the Superintendent to develop "Notices of Vacancy" for bargaining unit positions. Upon development, the Superintendent shall forward copies of proposed "Notice of Vacancy" for new supplemental positions and/or positions for which no vacancy notice exists to the ASSOCIATION President for input prior to formal implementation.</section>

<section prefix="f">Joint Supplemental Committee:</section>

<section>A joint supplemental committee will be established to review the supplemental salary schedule. The committee will be made up of the Assistant Superintendent or designeee (chair), Treasurer, Athletic Director, High School Administrator, Junior High Administrator, Elementary Administrator, one Association President, Fine Arts Advisor, Head Varsity Coach, Secondary Advisor, Elementary Advisor and one person identified by the ASSOCIATION. The committee shall meet prior to the beginning of the 2006 - 2007 school year, with the increases to total no more than twenty five thousand ($25,000) in total for that year. The committee shall meet no later than six months prior to the expiration of this AGREEMENT. The committee shall review the supplemental salary schedule and make a joint recommendation to the Association and Board negotiation teams.</section>
</text>

</law>