<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XVIII" level="1">Fringe Benefit Provisions</unit>
</structure>
	
<section_number>18.01</section_number>
<catch_line>Severance Pay</catch_line>
	
<text>(a) An employee who has been employed in the District for ten (10) years and who, upon leaving the employment of the District, retires and begins to receive benefits from the State Teachers Retirement System, State of Ohio, shall receive severance pay in an amount equal to twenty-five percent (25%) of the employee's accumulated but unused sick leave, including personal days converted to sick leave pursuant to other provisions of this Agreement in excess of the maximum sick leave accumulation, if appropriate to do so pursuant to such other provisions.

(b) Solely for the purposes of this Article, an employee with ten (10) years of service who dies while in active service of the Springboro Community City School District is deemed to have retired the day prior to his/her death.

(c) Severance pay shall be paid in January on the second payroll following the year of retirement of an employee, as elected by the Board.

18.02 Insurance Program

(a) Any Physician, Surgical, Major Medical, Dental, Vision and Prescription Drug Benefits Programs provided by this Agreement shall be the same or substantially similar to the plan currently in effect. However, in the event of the occurrence of one of the following events, the BOARD may provide another plan. The events are: the offered plan or a substantially similar plan, is no longer available; the plan or any other successor plan, increases in cost by 10% or more; or, the cost of a substantially similar plan is 10% or more than the cost of the plan currently in place. Prior to sending out the RFP, the Superintendent shall meet with the Insurance Committee, which includes the president of the Springboro Education Association and the president of the Springboro Classified Employees Association.

(b) The foregoing Physician, Surgical, Major Medical, Dental, Vision and Prescription Drug Benefits Programs shall be available for all employees on the active working payroll who have made application for such insurance on or before the effective date of this Agreement, who are regular employees employed by the BOARD, who either: (1) work at least half-time, and work at least thirty-six (36) weeks per year; or (2) have an annual contract with the BOARD, and for whom such coverage is in effect prior to the effective date of this Agreement.

(c) The foregoing Physician, Surgical, Major Medical, Dental, Vision and Prescription Drug Benefits Programs shall be available for all employees who make application for such insurance and/or such employees who are hired after the effective date of this Agreement, for all such employees who are regular employees of the BOARD, who either (1) work at least half-time and work at least thirty-six (36) weeks per year; or (2) have an annual contract with the BOARD and who complete the required insurance forms and have the same filed with the office of the Treasurer of the BOARD; provided, however, only employees presently covered only by the Prescription Drug Benefit Program may continue to be covered only by such benefit. All other employees must be covered by the Physician, Surgical, Major Medical and Prescription Drug benefits program. Upon completion and filing of the required insurance forms, on or prior to the thirtieth (30th) day of employment on the active working payroll, coverage becomes effective on the first day of the month following the month when first on the active working payroll.

(d) The foregoing Physician, Surgical, Major Medical, Dental, Vision and Prescription Drug Benefits Programs shall be provided to employees employed on a full-time basis, with full-time employees covered by such benefits contributing toward cost of such benefits based on the following schedule:

BOARD PORTION - 90% of the cost of each such benefit, as determined at least annually by the Insurance Administrator based on claims experience (single contract or family contract) or the insurance provider. The BOARD shall be responsible for any run off costs associated with the change from a self-insured program to an insured program.

EMPLOYEE PORTION - 10% of the cost of each such benefit, as determined at least annually by the Insurance Administrator based on claims experience (single contract or family contract) or the insurance provider.

The foregoing Physician/Surgical and Major Medical, Dental, Vision and Prescription Drug Benefit Program only shall be provided to employees employed on a less than full-time basis (less than thirty (30) hours per week), but employed under a regular contract by the BOARD with the BOARD‘s portion of the premium cost being determined based on the number of daily hours the part-time employee is under contract to perform service as a percentage of a full-time teaching contract (7 1/4 hours), such percentage being applied against the actual amount of the premium cost, reduced by the required full-time employee monthly contribution set forth in the foregoing schedule. Such part-time employee shall be responsible for the payment of all premium cost in excess of the BOARD's contribution toward such cost.

(e) The following Life Insurance Program shall be provided without cost to the full-time employees covered by this Agreement.

(1) Life insurance in the amount of $50,000.00 for all regular full-time employees who have an annual contract with the BOARD. Life insurance in the amount of $40,000.00 for all regular part-time employees who have an annual contract with the BOARD.

(2) Accidental Death and Dismemberment Insurance in the amount of $50,000.00 for all regular full-time employees who have an annual contract with the BOARD. Accidental Death and Dismemberment Insurance in the amount of $40,000.00 for all regular part-time employees who have an annual contract with the BOARD.

(3) The Life insurance specified in this Section shall be provided without cost to all employees who are on the active working payroll on the effective date of this Agreement, and who are regular employees of the BOARD, who have an annual contract with the BOARD, and for whom coverage is in effect immediately prior to the effective date of this Agreement. The insurance Program specified in this Section shall also be provided without cost to all regular employees and/or new employees who are hired after the effective date of this Agreement, effective on the first day of the month following the date of this Agreement or the date they commence actual employment with the BOARD, whichever is the later date, for all regular employees of the BOARD who have an annual contract with the BOARD.

(f) General Provisions

(1) The foregoing Physician, Surgical, Major Medical, Vision Care and Prescription Drug benefits described in Section 18.02(a) shall be continued for any eligible employee who pays the employee's portion as set forth in Section 18.02(d) during any period when such employee is on the active working payroll, compensated sick leave, compensated leave of absence granted pursuant to the provisions of this Agreement, non-compensated approved leave of absence of less than thirty (30) days, or for employees working only during the regular School year and not working during the Summer break period, until such employee either resign their employment status or fail to return to active working status at the commencement of the next school year. Except as otherwise required under the FMLA, employees on a non-compensated approved leave of absence of over thirty (30) days‘ duration, and/or employees or dependents of employees eligible for COBRA Benefit Continuation Rights who desire to continue benefit coverage described above in Sections 18.02(a) and (e) past the period for which the BOARD has agreed to continue benefit coverage for the employee may do so by paying one hundred and two percent (102%) of the full group premium for such insurance, as set by the BOARD's insurance Administrator or the insurance provider and/or insurance carrier, to the Administrator of the insurance program and/or the carrier designated by the BOARD and as set forth in COBRA regulations. In the event coverage is discontinued for any period, coverage cannot be reacquired through the BOARD until the employee returns to active working status.

(2) Unless a properly completed application form for any of the benefits described in Sections 18.02(d) and 18.02(e) is filed with the Treasurer of the BOARD within thirty (30) calendar days of the date the employee commences active working status, or returns to active working status from leave, whichever is applicable, or unless timely application is made for COBRA benefit rights, coverage will not be available until the next enrollment period and then in accordance with the limitations contained in the Plan.

(3) ln the event an employee desires to change from one type of coverage to a different type of coverage (e.g., single to dependent), the employee must follow the procedures specified in the "Master Plan Document". Any change in coverage shall be governed by the provisions contained in the "Master Plan Document".

(4) All benefits provided pursuant to this Benefit Program shall be subject to the conditions set forth in any contract secured by the BOARD or the conditions set forth in the "Master Plan Document".

(5) EFFECTIVE JANUARY 1, 2014, THE BOARD SHALL IMPLEMENT SPOUSAL LIMITATION LANGUAGE AS UTILIZED BY THE EPC.

(g) For purposes of this Article, the effective date of resignation of any employee shall be either: (1) the day prior to the commencement of the next school teaching year; or (2) the effective date of resignation as submitted on the employee's resignation notification, whichever date shall occur first.

18.03 STRS Pick-Up

(a) The BOARD herewith agrees with the ASSOCIATION to pick up (assume and pay) contributions to the State Teachers Retirement System upon behalf of the employees in the bargaining unit on the following terms and conditions:

(1) An amount equal to the employee's total contribution will be picked up and paid on behalf of each employee, including contributions on supplemental earnings.

(2) The BOARD shall compute and remit all applicable contributions to STRS based upon annual salaries and any other earned compensation(s).*

(3) The pick up percentage shall apply uniformly to all employees of the bargaining unit and no employee covered by this provision shall have the option to elect a wage increase or other benefit in lieu of the BOARD pick up.

(4) Definitions - " Annual salary - the adjusted salary plus the BOARD pick up of the employee's contribution to STRS. Adjusted salary - the annual salary minus the BOARD pick up (salary which appears on the employee's W-2 form).

(5) it is understood by the parties that computation of all supplemental salaries, extended time salaries, etc., will be computed upon the annual salary in effect at the time of computation.

(6) Said "pick up" shall not result in additional cost to the BOARD.

18.04 IRS Section 125 Plan

(a) The BOARD has in place a Section 125 Plan pursuant to which the employee portion of any insurance benefits and employee-paid medical expenses and employee-paid dependent care expenses may be paid with "before tax" dollars. The maximum amount which may be placed in this account for medical expenses during any calendar year shall be Two Thousand Dollars ($2,000.00). The maximum amount dependent care expenses IS Five Thousand Dollars ($5,000,000).

(b) The administrative cost of the Section 125 Plan shall be paid by the BOARD.

18.05 Mileage Reimbursement

(a) An employee required by the administration to drive his/her personal vehicle on School District business shall receive mileage reimbursement for such driving at the IRS mileage reimbursement rate. All vehicle usage must be approved in advance by the School administration and reimbursement must be requested on the appropriate form and approved by the appropriate Building Administrator for payment.

18.06 Tuition Reimbursement/Professional Development

(a) Tuition Reimbursement

(1) A fund of an annual appropriation of twenty three thousand dollars ($23,000) for the 2005-06 school year, thirty three thousand dollars ($33,000) for the 2006-07 school year, and forty three thousand dollars ($43,000) for the 2007-08 school year will be established to reimburse employees for tuition reimbursement. Funds will be distributed equally to employees based on total number of hours taken by all employees who have met the requirements of (2) below. The reimbursement shall be for tuition only and will not exceed actual tuition costs. The course work shall be completed prior to September 1 for the employee to receive reimbursement for the work done in the previous academic year (September - August). The employee must submit a transcript and receipt for the tuition to the Human Resources office by October 1. The employee will receive reimbursement by the first payroll of November if the employee is still under contract with the Board of Education at that time. A maximum of six (6) semester or nine (9) quarter hours per year will be eligible for reimbursement.

(2) All course work claimed for reimbursement shall:

a. Have been requested and approved on the proper form in advance of enrollment in the class.

b. Be in a field of education utilized by the School District.

c. Be graduate level from an accredited college or university.

d. Have been completed with a letter grade of "B" or better unless otherwise provided in connection with the approval to be deemed to have satisfactorily completed the course.

(b) Professional Development Stipend

(1) A fund of an annual appropriation of seven thousand dollars ($7,000) for each school year of the contract will be established to compensate employees for their attendance at professional development activities. Funds will be distributed equally to employees who have met the requirements of (2) below. In no case shall reimbursement to an employee exceed $7 per contact hour and $350 per employee per contract yar. Total reimbursement by the Board of Education for professional development will not exceed a total of seven thousand dollars ($7,000) per contract year. The employee must submit certificate(s) of attendance to the Director of Curriculum by October 1 for professional development attend from September 1 to August 31. The employee will receive the stipend by the first payroll of November.

(2) In order to be eligible for the professional development stipend, the employee shall have a minimum of 20 contact hours for the time period September 1 to August 31. In addition, the professional development must have received preapproval from the Director of Curriculum; be related to the employee's current working assignment and/or certification/licensure; and have been completed outside the contract day. Any professional development provided by the Board or for which the Board has paid the registration, expenses or some or all of the tuition shall not be eligible for the professional development stipend identified herein. An employee shall not receive both a processional development stipend and tuition reimbursement for the same coursework/activity.

(3) Any funds not disbursed for professional development stipends shall be transferred to the tuition reimbursement fund for that same contract year. No unused tuition reimbursement or professional development stipend funds shall be carried over from year to year.</text>

</law>