<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XIV" level="1">Leaves of Absence</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>14.05</section_number>
<catch_line>Personal Business Days</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">All employees will be credited with three (3) days personal business absence per year for businesses and personal reasons with the approval of the Superintendent. Such absence is not to be counted as sick leave. If personal days are unused, one day may be carried over to the next school year. Thus, the maximum number of personal days available in any one year would be four (4) days.</section>

<section prefix="b">Except in unforseen emergencies, as determined by the Superintendent, personal leave days shall not be granted on the first or last day of school, the day immediately prior to or following a school vacation or school holiday or on any in-service day or any parent-teacher conference day.</section>

<section prefix="c">If at the end of each school year an employee has any unused personal leave days, that employee may carry over one (1) day as described in paragraph (a) above or that employee may either transfer the unused personal leave to the employee's sick leave account up to the maximum accumulation allowed or cash out the unused personal days(s) at a rate of either five dollars ($85.00) per unused day. For employees who have the maximum number of six days accumulated, unused personal days (maximum of four (4) per year) may be converted to sick leave days, not to exceed ten (10) additional days. For employees who cash out the unused personal days(s), the payment shall not be considered as salary for STRS credit and will be made by separate check in a lump sum in July. An employee must inform the Treasurer in writing of his/her decision about what that employee wants to do with unused personal days by the teacher work day at the end of the school year. If an employee fails to notify the Treasurer by the date, then one personal day will be carried over to the net school year and any other unused personal days will be converted to sick leave in accordance with this paragraph.</section>

<section prefix="d">In calculating the severance pay for an employee eligible for severance pay, all accrued and unused personal days which the employee has will be automatically converted to sick leave days before severance pay is calculated.</section>
</text>

</law>