<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="IX" level="1">Vacancies, Assignments and Transfers</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>9.01</section_number>
<catch_line>Vacancy Announcements</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">A "vacancy" shall be defined as an "open position" within the bargaining unit covered by this AGREEMENT that the Administration determines to fill; provided, however, a vacancy shall not be deemed to exist for purposes of the procedures set forth in this Article if:</section>

<section prefix="1">if there is an employee in the bargaining unit on suspended contract with recall rights to the open position; or</section>

<section prefix="2">the Superintendent, in the exercise of his/her prerogative, fills the open position by involuntary transfer.</section>

<section prefix="b">Before filling a vacant position in the bargaining unit with an employee new to the district, the Superintendent shall notify present employees and the ASSOCIATION of the availability of the vacant position.</section>

<section prefix="c">During the school year, vacancy announcements to employees and the ASSOCIATION shall be by posting "Notices of Vacancy" in the school office in each building, with a copy to the ASSOCIATION President. During the summer months, notices shall be posted in the Central Office with a copy sent to the ASSOCIATION President. "Notices of Vacancy" shall include information regarding the building(s), grade level and certification required for the vacant position; the general duties and performance expectations/essential functions of the position, preferred job qualifications, if any, for the position and conditions of employment; and the internal application deadline and procedure for application.</section>

<section prefix="d">Present employees who are qualified by certificate for the position and who notify the Superintendent of their interest in the position will be considered for the position before individuals not in the employ of the BOARD are hired. if the applicant selected is a current employee, the Superintendent may determine to fill the vacancy with the employee during the school year or at the start of the next school year. If the determination is to wait until the start of the next school year to till the vacancy with a current employee, the vacancy may be filled on a temporary basis by another employee or a substitute for the remainder of the current school year. If the applicant selected is not a current employee, the vacancy may be filled by a new employee hired during the school year or by a substitute until the new employee is available.</section>

<section prefix="e">The Superintendent shall consider such factors as the professional background of the applicants, their seniority in the District (See Article XII, Section 12.01, Seniority Definition), their work performance and their experience elsewhere. The filling of each position shall be governed by the principle of selecting the best person for the position, as determined solely by the Superintendent.</section>

<section prefix="f">Except for an open position filed by involuntary transfer, applicants for other vacant positions will be considered in the following order:</section>

<section prefix="1">applicants seeking reassignment;</section>

<section prefix="2">displaced employees seeking voluntary transfer;</section>

<section prefix="3">employees seeking voluntary transfer; then</section>

<section prefix="4">others seeking employment with the District.</section>

<section prefix="g">For purposes of this section, the following definitions shall be:</section>

<section prefix="1">Reassignment: A change of subject or grade level assignment within the building.</section>

<section prefix="2">Transfer: A change of subject or grade level assignment from one building to another.</section>

<section prefix="3">Displaced Employee: An employee who is not assigned to the same teaching position and who is without an assignment.</section>
</text>

</law>