<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="VIII" level="1">Evaluation</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>8.04</section_number>
<catch_line>Evaluation Procedures</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">All observations and evaluations of work performance of an employee shall be conducted with full knowledge of the employee. Notification of the date and time of any announced observation shall be given to the employee in advance of the announced observation.</section>

<section prefix="b">Notwithstanding the provisions of the Ohio Revised Code which requires two (2) classroom observations, it is understood and mutually agreed by the ASSOCIATION and the BOARD that during the term of this Contract a formal "evaluation" shall be defined as at least one (1) announced observation of at least 30 minutes, but that other unannounced observations may occur. Evaluations shall reference employee strengths and deficiencies, as applicable, as well as one other documentation properly placed in the employee's personnel file.</section>

<section prefix="c">Employees who travel between buildings shall be evaluated by the principal/administrator as designated by the Superindendent, with written input from the principal(s)/administrators of the other building(s) to which the employees are assigned. The evaluation and any written input shall be placed in the employee's personnel file.</section>

<section prefix="d">Employees who are not new to the district may be evaluated more than one (1) time during a school year if deficiencies are noted on the first evaluation or at the discretion of the Administrator.</section>

<section prefix="3">A pro observation conference before announced observation between the observer and the employee to discuss observation/evaluation procedures and/or the focus of the observation/evaluation shall be held if the employee or building principal/administrator submits a written request.</section>

<section prefix="f">Within seven (7) days after an announced observation, written observation notes shall be provided to the employee. If an evaluator takes written observation notes during an unannounced observation, regardless of it's length, those notes shall be provided to the employee within seven (7) days of the observation.</section>

<section prefix="g">Within twenty one (21) days after the first announced observation, the written evaluation report shall be completed and a final evaluation conference shall be held between the evaluator and the employee. If a second evaluation is required, the written evaluation report and final evaluation conference will be held within twenty one (21) days of this second announced observation. At the conclusion of this final evaluation conference, the evaluator(s) and employee shall sign the evaluation report and the employee shall be given a copy of the signed and dated report. The signature of the employee will not indicate acceptance of the substance of the evaluation, but merely indicates that the employee has seen the evaluation.</section>

<section prefix="h">The employee may attach any comments concerning the evaluation he/she deems necessary. Such comments must be affixed within twenty-one (21) calendar days after the initial final evaluation conference but no later than the first Thursday in April for employees whose contracts expire, whichever date is earlier.</section>

<section prefix="i">The final, signed evaluation report, which shall be based on formal observations and other documentation properly judged for placement in the employee's personnel file (See Article VII), shall be forwarded to the Superindendent for review and placed in the employee's personnel file.</section>

<section prefix="j">The Self-Evaluation will be shared with the evaluator at the final evaluation conference of the year.</section>
</text>

</law>