<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XVII" level="1">Salary Schedule Provisions</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>17.02</section_number>
<catch_line>Placement on the Salary Schedule</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">The Superintendent may, in the exercise of his sole discretion, and notwithstanding any provision in the Ohio Revised Code which might mandate otherwise, grant up to fifteen (15) full years of teaching experience credit for salary placement purposes to any employee based on the prior teaching experience of such certified employees whether such experience was gained in the State of Ohio or otherwise, or in private or public schools. This provision shall apply to employees hired after August 26, 2002. Employees hired after July 1, 2002 will have their checks electronically deposited (Direct Deposit) to a Financial Institution of their choice.</section>

<section prefix="b">Requirements for receiving credit on the BA+15 Column are 15 graduate semester hours taken from an accredited university or college after receipt of the BA/BS degree which are in the field of education or directly related to the certified employee's present assignment or area of certification. Requirements for receiving credit on the MA+15 or MA+30 column are 15 or 30 semester hours taken from an accredited university or college after receipt of the MA degree which are in the field of education or directly related to the certified employee's present assignment or areas of certification. Video courses from an accredited university or college must be approved in advance by the Superintendent. In order to submit a "video course" for approval by the Superintendent, the employee must furnish:</section>

<section prefix="1">verification, in writing, from an Administrator of the University of College offering the course that such course is a graduate level course;

<section prefix="2">verification that the course, if successfully completed, will be accepted for credit towards an advanced degree by the University or College which the employee is enrolled in and pursuing such a degree; and

<section prefix="3">the syllabus for the course as issued by the University or College offering the course.

<section prefix="c">The AFROTC instructor shall receive the greater of the approved salary schedule for his/her training and experience or the minimum instructor's pay as provided by the approved AFROTC program.</section>

<section prefix="d">Employees who qualify for lateral movement on the salary schedule shall be granted such lateral movement:</section>

<section prefix="1">effective with the new contract year, providing an official university transcript certifying completion of the work is forwarded to the Treasurer by October 1; or

<section prefix="2">effective with the first pay in March, providing an official university transcript certifying completion of the work is forwarded to the Treasurer by February 15th.

<section prefix="e">Each step on the salary schedule represents a full year of service. A full year of service at a minimum consists of at least one hundred and twenty (120) days in pay status under a teacher contract during a school year. Teachers who do not meet this minimum teaching requirement in any year will not be advanced to the next step during the following school year. This Section shall be effective with the commencement of the 1998-99 school year and will not be retroactively appealed to cause any employee to be reduced in Grade Step at the start of the 1998-99 school year from the Grade Step the employee was in during the 1997-98 school year.</section>
</text>

</law>