<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="1" level="1">Recognition</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>1.01</section_number>
<catch_line>Definition of Bargaining Unit</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">The Springboro Community City School District Board of Education, hereinafter referred to as the "BOARD", recognizes the Springboro Education Association, OEA/NEA, hereinafter referred to as the "ASSOCIATION", as the exclusive and sole collective bargaining representative for all purposes permitted by Chapter 4117 of the Ohio Revised Code for all certificated/licensed employees under Ohio Revised Code Title 33 including regular classroom teachers, special education teachers, counselors, librarians, nurses, I/SG instructors (tutors) and school psychologists but excluding all substitutes, "auxiliary service" employees, administrative staff and/or supervisory employees, as defined in Chapter 4117 of the Ohio Revised Code, and all other employees of the BOARD. These exclusions shall include the Superintendent, Assistant Superintendent, Treasurer, Directors Principals, Assistant Principals, Coordinator(s), Athletic Director and Business Manager.</section>

<section prefix="b">As used in this AGREEMENT, the term "employee(s)" refers to all employee(s) included in the bargaining unit described above in Section 1.01(a).</section>
</text>

<section_number>1.02</section_number>
<catch_line>Management Rights of the Board</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">The ASSOCIATION recognizes the BOARD as the locally elected body charged with the establishment of policy of public education in the Springboro Community City School District and as the employer of all personnel of this school system under State law. The ASSOCIATION further recognizes that the BOARD has the sole responsibility for the management and control of all the public schools of whatever name or character in the District and has the full authority to establish the rules and regulations by which the District will be governed as provided in the Ohio Revised Code, except as limited by specific provisions of this Contract.</section>

<section prefix="b">It is specifically agreed that the BOARD has all management rights set forth in Section 4117.08 of the Ohio Revised Code.</section>

<section prefix="c">The term Superintendent used herein shall mean the Superintendent or his designee.</section>

<section prefix="d">The ASSOCIATION recognizes the BOARD as the locally elected body charged with the establishment of a policy of public education of the Springboro Community School District and as the employer of all personnel of the school system under state law. The ASSOCIATION further recognizes that the BOARD has the responsibility for the management and control of all the public schools of whatever name or character in the District and is specifically delegated with the responsibility of making the rules and regulations by which the District will be governed as Chapter Ohio Revised Code section 3313.20, Ohio Revised Code section 3313.47, Chapter 124 and Chapter 4117 of the Ohio Revised Code except as modified by this agreement.</section>
</text>

</law>