<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XII" level="1">Seniority/Reduction in Force/Recall</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>12.03</section_number>
<catch_line>Reduction in Force</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">When a staff reduction is necessary, as determined by the BOARD, the Superintendent shall give written notice by the certified mail of the intent to recommend the suspension of contracts to the employees so affected and the ASSOCIATION President. A list of all those affected shall be given to the ASSOCIATION. The notification to the employees and the ASSOCIATION shall be given eight (8) calendar days prior to the BOARD meeting at which action will be taken on the reduction in force in order to allow the ASSOCIATION to confer with the Superintendent about the reasons for the reduction.</section>

<section prefix="b">Implementation of a reduction in force shall occur at no other time than the beginning of a school year, expect for reductions made necessary the return of an employee from a leave of absence.</section>

<section prefix="c">Reduction(s) shall be made through attrition resulting from resignations, retirements, non-renewals, terminations and transfers, with the vacancies created by such resignations, retirements, non-renewals, terminations or transfers filled utilizing the procedures set forth in Article IX.</section>

<section prefix="d">Secondly, if additional reductions are necessary, non-tenured employees in the certification area(s) affected by the reduction will be reduced on the basis of last senior, first to be reduced, by certification area, as noted on the seniority list.</section>

<section prefix="e">If additional reductions are necessary, tenured employees in the certification area(s) affected by the reduction will be reduced on the basis of least senior, first to be reduced, by certification area or position, as noted by the priority list.</section>

<section prefix="f">Employees who are displaced and/or reduced from one teaching area but who hold a valid certificate in another area taught in the District may exercise their seniority to displace the least senior employee in the other teaching area; provided a non-tenured employee shall not have the right to displace a tenured employee and, provided further, the senior employee desiring to exercise this displacement right has either:</section>

<section prefix="1">taught in this teaching area within the past four (4) years; or

<section prefix="2">can demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Superintendent the present ability to teach the subject(s) involved. The Superintendent's decision shall not be arbitrary and capricious. Any employee wishing to exercise this right of displacement must notify the superintendent, by certified mail, within seven (7) days of the date the employee receives his/her notice of reduction as required by Section 12.03(a).

<section prefix="g">After all reduction/displacement alternatives are exercise, the employees who are unable to exercise such rights will have their reaching contracts suspended.</section>
</text>

</law>