<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="V" level="1">Association Rights</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>5.11</section_number>
<catch_line>Fair Share Fee</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">Payroll Deduction of Fair Share Fee</section>

<section prefix="a">The Board shall deduct from the pay of employees who elect not to become or to remain members of the ASSOCIATION, a fair share fee for the ASSOCIATION'S representation of such nonmembers during the term of this contract. No non-member filing a timely demand shall be required to subsidize partisan political or ideological causes not germane to the ASSOCIATION'S work in the realm of collective bargaining.</section>

<section prefix="b">Notification of the amount of Fair Share Fee</section>

<section prefix="a">Notice of the amount of the annual fair share fee, which shall not be more than 100% of the unified dues of the ASSOCIATION, shall be transmitted by the ASSOCIATION to the Treasurer of the Board on or about September 15 of each year during the term of this contract for the purpose of determining amounts to be payroll deducted, and the BOARD agrees to promptly transmit all amounts deducted to the ASSOCIATION.</section>

<section prefix="c">Schedule of Fair Share Fee Donations</section>

<section prefix="1">All Fair Share Fee Payers</section>

<section prefix="a">Payroll deductions of such annual fair share fees shall commenced on the first pay date which occurs on or after January 15th annually. In the case of unit employees newly haired after the beginning of the school year, the payroll deduction shall commence on the first pay date or or after the later of:</section>

<section prefix="a">Sixty (60) days employment in a bargaining unit position or</section>

<section prefix="b">January 15th.</section>

<section prefix="2">Upon termination of membership during the membership year the Treasurer of the BOARD shall, upon notification from the ASSOCIATION that a member has terminated membership, commence the deduction of the fair share fee with respect to the former member, and the amount of the fee yet to be deducted shall be the annual fair share fee less the amount previously paid through payroll deduction.</section>

<section prefix="d">Transmittal of Deductions</section>

<section prefix="a">The BOARD further agrees to accompany each such transmittal with a list of names of the employees for whom all such fair share fee deductions were made, the period covered, and the amounts deducted for each.</section>

<section prefix="e">Procedure for Rebate</section>

<section prefix="1">The ASSOCIATION represents to the BOARD that an internal rebate procedure has been established in accordance with Section 4117.09(C) of the revised code and that a procedure for challenging the amount of the representation fee has been established and will be given to each member of the bargaining unit who does not join the ASSOCIATION and that such procedure shall be in compliance with all applicable state and federal laws and the constitutions of the United States and the State of Ohio.</section>

<section prefix="f">Entitlement to Rebate</section>

<section prefix="1">Upon timely demand, non-members may apply to the ASSOCIATION for an advance rebate of the fair share fee pursuant to the internal procedure adopted by the ASSOCIATION.</section>

<section prefix="g">Indemnification of Employer</section>

<section prefix="1">The ASSOCIATION, on behalf of itself and the OEA and NEA, agrees to indemnify the BOARD for any cost or liability incurred as a result of the implementation and enforcement of this provision provided that:</section>

<section prefix="a">the BOARD shall give a ten (10) day written notice of any claim made or action filed against the employer by a non-member for which indemnification may be claimed;</section>

<section prefix="b">The ASSOCIATION shall reserve the right to designate counsel to represent and defend the employer;</section>

<section prefix="c">The BOARD agrees to: (1) Give full and complete cooperation and assistance to the ASSOCIATION and its counsel at all levels of the proceeding; (2) Permit the ASSOCIATION or its affiliates to intervene as a party if it so desires, and/or (3) TO not oppose the ASSOCIATION or its affiliates' application to file briefs amious curiae in the action;</section>

<section prefix="d">The BOARD acted in good fail compliance with the fair share fee provision of this agreement; however there shall be no indemnification of the BOARD if the BOARD intentionally or willfully fails to apply (except due to court order) or misapply such fair share fee provision herein.</section>
</text>

</law>