<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XVII" level="1">Salary Schedule Provisions</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>17.01</section_number>
<catch_line>COMPENSATION Salary Schedule and Index</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">The base salary effective with the 2005-2006 school year shall be $32,722; the base salary effective with the 2006-2007 school year shall be $33,605; and the base salary effective with the 2007-2008 school year shall be $34,563. Appendix D is a copy of the salary schedules and indices for the three school years.</section>
</text>

<section_number>17.02</section_number>
<catch_line>Placement on the Salary Schedule</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">The Superintendent may, in the exercise of his sole discretion, and notwithstanding any provision in the Ohio Revised Code which might mandate otherwise, grant up to fifteen (15) full years of teaching experience credit for salary placement purposes to any employee based on the prior teaching experience of such certified employees whether such experience was gained in the State of Ohio or otherwise, or in private or public schools. This provision shall apply to employees hired after August 26, 2002. Employees hired after July 1, 2002 will have their checks electronically deposited (Direct Deposit) to a Financial Institution of their choice.</section>

<section prefix="b">Requirements for receiving credit on the BA+15 Column are 15 graduate semester hours taken from an accredited university or college after receipt of the BA/BS degree which are in the field of education or directly related to the certified employee's present assignment or area of certification. Requirements for receiving credit on the MA+15 or MA+30 column are 15 or 30 semester hours taken from an accredited university or college after receipt of the MA degree which are in the field of education or directly related to the certified employee's present assignment or areas of certification. Video courses from an accredited university or college must be approved in advance by the Superintendent. In order to submit a "video course" for approval by the Superintendent, the employee must furnish:</section>

<section prefix="1">verification, in writing, from an Administrator of the University of College offering the course that such course is a graduate level course;

<section prefix="2">verification that the course, if successfully completed, will be accepted for credit towards an advanced degree by the University or College which the employee is enrolled in and pursuing such a degree; and

<section prefix="3">the syllabus for the course as issued by the University or College offering the course.

<section prefix="c">The AFROTC instructor shall receive the greater of the approved salary schedule for his/her training and experience or the minimum instructor's pay as provided by the approved AFROTC program.</section>

<section prefix="d">Employees who qualify for lateral movement on the salary schedule shall be granted such lateral movement:</section>

<section prefix="1">effective with the new contract year, providing an official university transcript certifying completion of the work is forwarded to the Treasurer by October 1; or

<section prefix="2">effective with the first pay in March, providing an official university transcript certifying completion of the work is forwarded to the Treasurer by February 15th.

<section prefix="e">Each step on the salary schedule represents a full year of service. A full year of service at a minimum consists of at least one hundred and twenty (120) days in pay status under a teacher contract during a school year. Teachers who do not meet this minimum teaching requirement in any year will not be advanced to the next step during the following school year. This Section shall be effective with the commencement of the 1998-99 school year and will not be retroactively appealed to cause any employee to be reduced in Grade Step at the start of the 1998-99 school year from the Grade Step the employee was in during the 1997-98 school year.</section>
</text>

<section_number>17.03</section_number>
<catch_line>Supplemental Salary Schedule</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">The supplemental salary schedule base shall be computed as follows:</section>

<section prefix="1">0-3 years experience 13.5% of BA 0
<section prefix="2">4-6 years experience 15.5% of BA 0
<section prefix="3">7+ years experience 17.5% of BA 0

<section prefix="b">Placement on the supplemental salary schedule shal be according to the following guidelines:</section>

<section prefix="1">Years of experience as a paid employee shall be granted for the total number of years experience in the specific activity/coaching field; i.e., football, basketball, track, etc.</section>

<section prefix="2">Assistant coaches appointed to a head coaching position within the same port shall be placed at the lowest experience level which provides a salary higher than their current assistant coach salary levels.</section>

<section prefix="3">Experience in boys and girls sports shall be treated equally with regard to experience, providing such experience is within the same specific activity/coaching field.</section>

<section prefix="c">Adjustments in Index factors for any supplemental position and/or creation of new supplemental positions during the term of this Agreement shall be made if there is mutual agreement between the BOARD and the ASSOCIATION.</section>

<section prefix="d">Notwithstanding the wage rate specified in Appendix X for the Camp Kern Counselor, past experience in the positions where experience has not been applicable shall not be granted. The 1994-95 school year shall be considered the first year of experience for placement on the salary schedule.</section>

<section prefix="e">Development of "Notices of Vacancy" for supplemental positions shall be according to the following guidelines:</section>

<section prefix="1">"Notice of Vacancy" postings shall be prepared for all new supplemental positions prior to posting and filing said positions.

<section prefix="2">It is the prerogative of the Superintendent to develop "Notices of Vacancy" for bargaining unit positions. Upon development, the Superintendent shall forward copies of proposed "Notice of Vacancy" for new supplemental positions and/or positions for which no vacancy notice exists to the ASSOCIATION President for input prior to formal implementation.</section>

<section prefix="f">Joint Supplemental Committee:</section>

<section>A joint supplemental committee will be established to review the supplemental salary schedule. The committee will be made up of the Assistant Superintendent or designeee (chair), Treasurer, Athletic Director, High School Administrator, Junior High Administrator, Elementary Administrator, one Association President, Fine Arts Advisor, Head Varsity Coach, Secondary Advisor, Elementary Advisor and one person identified by the ASSOCIATION. The committee shall meet prior to the beginning of the 2006 - 2007 school year, with the increases to total no more than twenty five thousand ($25,000) in total for that year. The committee shall meet no later than six months prior to the expiration of this AGREEMENT. The committee shall review the supplemental salary schedule and make a joint recommendation to the Association and Board negotiation teams.</section>
</text>

<section_number>17.04</section_number>
<catch_line>Stipends for Curriculum Development</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">Notwithstanding any provision in the Ohio Revised Code which might require otherwise, employees participating in curriculum development activities as approved by the Superintendent, or employees sewing on the LPDC, shall be paid an hourly rate for each hour worked, which hourly rate shall not be based on their degree status or longevity. During the term of this Agreement, the hourly rate payable to employees engaged in curriculum development activities or sewing on the LPDC shall be computed at .00075 of the BA Step 0 base.</section>

<section prefix="b">Employees who volunteer to work during the summer in the following areas shall be paid $75.00 per day for: (1) Textbook/Course of Study Coding; (2) Subject Area in-service provided by the District; and/or (3) School-wide In-service provided by the District.</section>
</text>

<section_number>17.05</section_number>
<catch_line>Summer School Teachers/Home Tutors/After School Intervention</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">Notwithstanding any provision in the Ohio Revised Code which might require otherwise, employees employed to teach in summer school or employed to teach as home tutors shall be paid an hourly rate for each hour worked, which hourly rate shall not be based on their degree status or longevity. During the term of this AGREEMENT, the hourly rate payable to summer school teachers and home tutors shall be computed at .00075 of the BA Step 0 base.</section>
</text>

<section_number>17.06</section_number>
<catch_line>Saturday School/Administrative Detention</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">Notwithstanding any provision in the Ohio Revised Code which might require otherwise, employees employed to supervise or conduct Saturday school activities shall be paid a daily rate of Sixty Dollars ($60.00) for each Saturday session worked, which daily rate shall not be based on their degree, status or longevity. Each Saturday School session will be three (3) hours in duration.</section>

<section prefix="b">Employees assigned to supervise Saturday School will be selected in accordance with the following procedures:</section>

<section prefix="1">At the commencement of each school year employees will be advised of the need for employees to supervise Saturday School sessions during the school year and will be asked to "sign up" to indicate a willingness to perform this assignment. There will be at least a seven (7) calendar day period during which employees may "sign up" for this assignment.</section>

<section prefix="2">During the school year, from among those employees who "sign up" to accept such assignment, the Superintendent will select an employee on a rotating basis to work each Saturday School session before any employee is assigned to a second Saturday School session.</section>

<section prefix="c">Notwithstanding any provision in the Ohio Revised Code which might require otherwise, employees employed to supervise or conduct Administrative Detention activities shall be paid an hourly rate of Twenty Dollars ($20.00) per hour for each administrative detention session worked, which hourly rate shall not be based on their degree, status or longevity.</section>
</text>

<section_number>17.07</section_number>
<catch_line>Elementary Required Evening Music Program</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">Employees who supervise the evening elementary music program shall be paid at the rate of Forty Dollars ($40.00) per music program.</section>
</text>

</law>