<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XVI" level="1">Individual Employee Contracts</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>16.01</section_number>
<catch_line>Limited Contract Sequence</catch_line>
	
<text>
<section prefix="a">An employee sewing under a limited contract shall be considered, at the expiration of his/her present limited contract, for a multi-year limited contract, providing the following qualifications have been met:</section>

<section prefix="1">The employee has served at least three consecutive years under one-year limited contracts.</section>

<section prefix="2">The employee is recommended on the basis of evaluation for a multi-year contract by the Superintendent.</section>

<section prefix="3">Nothing herein shall preclude the BOARD from offering the employee a one-year contract on the basis of evaluation.</section>
</text>

<section_number>16.02</section_number>
<catch_line>Continuing Contracts</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">At the Expiration of a Limited Contract</section>

<section>If an employee, including employees who have attained continuing contract status elsewhere, becomes eligible for continuing contract status at the expiration of his/her current limited contract, the BOARD may enter into a continuing contract with that employee at the commencement of the School year after the expiration of the employee's limited contract after such employee becomes eligible, provided that:</section>

<section prefix="1">No employee shall have a right to a continuing contract unless such employee has given notice of his/her desire to be considered for a continuing contract by December 1 of the school year proceeding the school year for which the employee desires the continuing contract.</section>

<section prefix="b">During Term of Limited Contract</section>

<section>If an employee, including an employee who has attained continuing contract status elsewhere, becomes eligible for continuing contract status before the expiration of his/her current multi-year limited contract, the BOARD may enter into a continuing contract with that employee at the commencement of the school year after the employee becomes eligible; provided that:</section>

<section prefix="1">the employee notifies the Superintendent, in writing, prior to October first of the school year during which the employee will become eligible for a continuing contract that he/she will be completing his/her requirements and will be eligible for a continuing contract during the term of said limited contract;

<section prefix="2">the employee meets all requirements for a continuing contract before the start of the new contract and evidence of such achievement is on file with the Superintendent prior to the start of the school year; and

<section prefix="3">The Superintendent believes that such employee should be issued a continuing contract and so recommends to the Board.</section>

<section prefix="c">Determinations of the Superintendent and/or the BOARD under this section are not appealable under the Grievance/Arbitration provisions of this AGREEMENT.</section>

<section prefix="d">Should the employee fail to provide the written notice required by paragraph (a) (1), the Board may issue the employee a one year limited contract.</section>

<section prefix="e">The provisions of this Article specifically supersede the relevant portions of Ohio Revised Code section 3319.111 and any other conflicting section of the Ohio Revised Code.</section>
</text>

<section_number>16.03</section_number>
<catch_line>Supplemental Contracts</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">The supplemental teaching contract tor an extra-duty assignment which grants additional compensation shall be a limited contract and shall be separate from and in addition to the regular teaching contract of any employee.</section>

<section prefix="b">The supplemental teaching contract shall be for one (1) year and shall automatically expire at the end of the contract year.</section>

<section prefix="c">Each supplemental teaching contract shall include the specific supplemental agreement; salary and date(s) of payment; and signatures of both parties to the contract and the date of the signing of the contract.</section>
</text>

</law>