<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XIV" level="1">Leaves of Absence</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>14.08</section_number>
<catch_line>Professional Leave</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">An employee wishing to request professional leave shall do so on the designated District form at least ten (10) calendar days prior to the meeting or conference. Said request shall be approved or rejected by the Principal and Superintendent in advance of the meeting or conference.</section>

<section prefix="b">Attendance is limited to one employee from a department or office at any one meeting except as approved by the Superintendent. Presenters shall have priority in being granted Professional Leave provided approval is secured prior to the employee agreeing to be a presenter.</section>

<section prefix="c">Expense Reimbursement:</section>

<section prefix="1">Travel expenses shall be reimbursed at the then current IRS-approved mileage rate for reimbursement, or air tourist rates, whichever is less.</section>

<section prefix="2">Meal and lodging allowance shall be paid at a per diem rate of not more than One Hundred Twenty-five Dollars ($125.00) per day provided that receipts for all expenditures are attached to the designated reimbursement request.</section>

<section prefix="3">The meal allowance for one (1) meal during a full one day workshop shall not exceed Fifteen Dollars ($15.00) per day, provided that receipts for all expenditures are attached to the designated reimbursement request.</section>

<section prefix="4">Registration fees shall be reimbursed at the advertised conference rate. When cost of meals is included in the registration fee, no other voucher for meals will be honored.</section>

<section prefix="5">Because of budget constraints, professional meeting reimbursements may be less than the actual anticipated and/or incurred expenses. The administration shall make the employee aware of this limitation prior to the approval of the meeting.</section>
</text>

</law>