<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XIV" level="1">Leaves of Absence</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>14.09</section_number>
<catch_line>Fulbright Teacher Exchange Leave</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">An employee with at least (5) years of continuous employment with the Springboro Community City School District dating from the employee's most recent date of hire may, with permission of the BOARD be entitled to take a leave of absence from teaching duties with full salary and benefits for up to one (1) year to participate in Fulbright Teacher Exchange Program.</section>

<section prefix="b">Participation in the Fulbright Exchange Program shall be subject to the following conditions:</section>

<section prefix="1">The year the employee participates in the Fulbright Exchange Program shall count as a year of service in the Springboro Community City Schools.</section>

<section prefix="2">Application for permission to participate much be submitted prior to September 1 in the year preceding the year in which the leave is to be taken.</section>

<section prefix="3">The Fulbright Teacher Exchange Program must approve the employee's participation in the program and must provide an exchange replacement employee to the School District to teach in the position of Springboro employee granted the leave from assigned teaching duties at no cost to the BOARD for any wages, benefits or other expense of the provided employee.</section>

<section prefix="4">The employee, who must agree to work for the Springboro Community City School District for one (1) year following completion of the program, shall be returned to his/her same position upon return.</section>

<section prefix="5">Participation in the Exchange Program shall result in no additional cost to the District.</section>

<section prefix="6">The exchange employee shall not be deemed an employee of the School District but shall be subject to all rules, regulations and policies of the BOARD, the same as an employee who would bound by such rules, regulations and policies.</section>

<section prefix="7">If the exchange employee, for whatever reason, cannot fulfill his/her responsibilities for the term of the exchange, the Springboro employees shall return to the District at such time as the exchange employee leaves the District.</section>

<section prefix="c">No more than one (1) employee may participate in a Fulbright Teacher Exchange Program in any school year.</section>
</text>

</law>