<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XVIII" level="1">Fringe Benefit Provisions</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>18.06</section_number>
<catch_line>Tuition Reimbursement/Professional Development</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">Tuition Reimbursement</section>

<section prefix="1">A fund of an annual appropriation of twenty three thousand dollars ($23,000) for the 2005-06 school year, thirty three thousand dollars ($33,000) for the 2006-07 school year, and forty three thousand dollars ($43,000) for the 2007-08 school year will be established to reimburse employees for tuition reimbursement. Funds will be distributed equally to employees based on total number of hours taken by all employees who have met the requirements of (2) below. The reimbursement shall be for tuition only and will not exceed actual tuition costs. The course work shall be completed prior to September 1 for the employee to receive reimbursement for the work done in the previous academic year (September - August). The employee must submit a transcript and receipt for the tuition to the Human Resources office by October 1. The employee will receive reimbursement by the first payroll of November if the employee is still under contract with the Board of Education at that time. A maximum of six (6) semester or nine (9) quarter hours per year will be eligible for reimbursement.</section>

<section prefix="2">All course work claimed for reimbursement shall:</section>

<section prefix="a">Have been requested and approved on the proper form in advance of enrollment in the class.</section>

<section prefix="b">Be in a field of education utilized by the School District.</section>

<section prefix="c">Be graduate level from an accredited college or university.</section>

<section prefix="d">Have been completed with a letter grade of "B" or better unless otherwise provided in connection with the approval to be deemed to have satisfactorily completed the course.</section>

<section prefix="b">Professional Development Stipend</section>

<section prefix="1">A fund of an annual appropriation of seven thousand dollars ($7,000) for each school year of the contract will be established to compensate employees for their attendance at professional development activities. Funds will be distributed equally to employees who have met the requirements of (2) below. In no case shall reimbursement to an employee exceed $7 per contact hour and $350 per employee per contract yar. Total reimbursement by the Board of Education for professional development will not exceed a total of seven thousand dollars ($7,000) per contract year. The employee must submit certificate(s) of attendance to the Director of Curriculum by October 1 for professional development attend from September 1 to August 31. The employee will receive the stipend by the first payroll of November.</section>

<section prefix="2">In order to be eligible for the professional development stipend, the employee shall have a minimum of 20 contact hours for the time period September 1 to August 31. In addition, the professional development must have received preapproval from the Director of Curriculum; be related to the employee's current working assignment and/or certification/licensure; and have been completed outside the contract day. Any professional development provided by the Board or for which the Board has paid the registration, expenses or some or all of the tuition shall not be eligible for the professional development stipend identified herein. An employee shall not receive both a processional development stipend and tuition reimbursement for the same coursework/activity.</section>

<section prefix="3">Any funds not disbursed for professional development stipends shall be transferred to the tuition reimbursement fund for that same contract year. No unused tuition reimbursement or professional development stipend funds shall be carried over from year to year.</section>
</text>

</law>