<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<law>

<structure>
	<unit label="Article" identifier="XIV" level="1">Leaves of Absence</unit>
</structure>

<section_number>14.03</section_number>
<catch_line>Medical/Disability Leave</catch_line>

<text>
<section prefix="a">Upon application and formal BOARD approval, an employee shall be granted an unpaid, medical or disability leave of absence in accordance with Section 3319.13 of the Ohio Revised Code. Said leave shall be for a period of time not to exceed one (1) year from the effective date of the leave, but will be extended for an additional period or periods to a maximum of two (2) total years of medical/disability leave upon submission of appropriate disability verification. All applications for unpaid leave shall include a termination date of the leave.</section>

<section prefix="b">An employee on a school-year medical leave of absence shall verify in writing by March 15 to the Superintendent his/her desire to return to work the following school year. If the return date is in the middle of a school year, the employee shall verify to the Superintendent his/her desire to return to work within thirty (30) calendar days of the end of the leave. These timelines may be waived by mutual consent of both parties.</section>

<section prefix="c">An employee returning to work following an approved medical/disability leave of absence must furnish the Superintendent with a statement from his/her attending physician certifying the employee's ability to return to active working status. lf the employee's physician is unable to certify that the employee is able to resume his/her full and normal job duties without limitations, the attending physician shall provide the full particulars on any limitations/restrictions in place and the likely duration of such. In the event there are restrictions/limitations, a meeting will be held with the employee before a determination is made on whether the employee may/may not return to active working status. If as a result of this meeting the Superintendent determines that the employee can return to work with restrictions/limitations, the Superintendent and the employee will then work out the reasonable accommodations necessary, if possible, to enable the employee to do so.</section>

<section prefix="d">The Superintendent may, in the exercise of his sole discretion, require any employee desiring to return to active working status to be examined by a physician or physicians selected by the Superintendent for the purpose of confirming that the employee is able to return to work with or without restrictions/limitations and if the employee is able to return to work with restrictions/limitations, to work out the reasonable accommodations necessary, if possible, to enable the employee to do so.</section>

<section>In the event the employee's physician and the physician selected by the Superintendent do not agree on any matter, they shall jointly refer the matter to a third physician mutually acceptable to such physicians who shall consider the reports of the two physicians, examine the employee, if necessary, and determine the matter at issue. The determination of this third physician shall be binding on all concerned and is not subject to further appeal.</section>

<section>The employee is responsible for all expenses incurred from his/her physician.</section>

<section>The BOARD is responsible for all expenses incurred from the physician selected by the Superintendent and for the cost of the third physician.</section>
</text>

</law>